Guide to the Shanklin Laboratory Renovation Records, 1967-1978
Shanklin Laboratory Renovation Records, 1967 - 1978
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
2010-4
0.5
1
Shanklin Laboratory at Wesleyan University was completed in 1928 and underwent major renovation from the mid-1960s through the mid-1970s.
The Shanklin Laboratory Renovation Records concern the Biology Department’s involvement with the proposed renovations of Shanklin Laboratory, occurring between 1967 and 1978. Materials included in this collection are planning correspondence (memoranda, letters, and personal notes), itemized work estimates, cost estimates and bills, blueprints, contracts, and floor plans (both formal and informal). Haines, Lundberg and Waehler were the major architects involved in this project. Science Center Director Ross Gortner, Facilities Planner Robert Wilson, Vice President of Business Affiars Donald Bruster, and Professors Vincent W. Cochrane, Earl Hanson, and Barry Keifer are the primary correspondents in the collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Received from the Biology Department in November 2009 (Accession #2010-4).
Historical Note
Shanklin Laboratory at Wesleyan University was originally built in the late 1920s, finished in 1928. The funds for the building were donated by the friends of late University president William Arnold Shanklin, and its construction was part of a 1.25 million dollar building initiative on campus. The Shanklin renovation initiative (beginning in 1963) was a result of the University’s decision to increase the size of the student body by 510, and to put a greater emphasis on scientific research and competitive science programming. Additionally, the University was pushing forward a huge building plan for the new Science Center (renamed Exley Science Center in 2002), which broke ground in 1965. The Shanklin renovations were completed in pieces; most phases were done room by room as funds became available. Accordingly, many of the papers in this collection are correspondence between individual professors and administrators lobbying for personal offices and labs to be renovated and updated. A summary of all renovations completed year-by-year can be found in Folder 17 (Subseries 5.1: Planning Correspondence).
Collection Overview
This collection is organized into 5 main series, representing a chronological progression of documents. Series 1 contains documents from the years 1967 to 1970, Series 2 from the year 1972, Series 3 from the year 1973, Series 4 from the year 1974, and Series 5 details the years 1976 to 1978. Each series (with the exception of Series 5) contains four subseries: Planning Correspondence, Itemized Work Estimates, Cost Estimates and Bills, and Blueprints and Floor plans (Series 5 does not contain a folder for the last subseries, Blueprints and Floor plans). The most prevalent documents in the collection are informal correspondence between small groups of Biology professors or individual professors and Ross Gortner, Director of the Science Center. Also included are correspondence with planning firms, and lab equipment providers (generally Gortner or Facilities Planner Robert Wilson represent the University in these inquiries). There are also several full blueprints which show large-scale plans for renovation which were not completed during this period.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Buildings.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Biology Dept.; College buildings--Designs and plans.; Architectural drawings; Haines, Lundberg & Waehler; Cochrane, Vincent W.; Gortner, Ross Aiken, 1912-1988.; Bruster, Donald.; Keifer, Barry.; Hanson, Earl D.
Related Material
Shanklin Hall Vertical Files, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: 1967-1970
  - Subseries 1.1, Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 1.2, Itemized Work Estimates (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 1.3, Cost Estimates and Bills (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 1.4, Blueprints and Floor Plans (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series 2: 1972
  - Subseries 2.1, Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2.2, Itemized Work Estimates (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2.3, Cost Estimates and Bills (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2.4, Blueprints and Floor Plans (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 3: 1973
  - Subseries 3.1, Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3.2, Itemized Work Estimates (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 3.3, Cost Estimates and Bills (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3.4, Blueprints and Floor Plans (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 4: 1974
  - Subseries 4.1, Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 4.2, Itemized Work Estimates (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 4.3, Cost Estimates and Bills (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 4.4, Blueprints and Floor Plans (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 5: 1976-1978
  - Subseries 5.1, Planning Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 5.2, Itemized Work Estimates (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 5.3, Blueprints and Floor Plans (Box 1, Folder 19)